Finding Aid for the Sarah Bixby Smith Correspondence LSC.0223
UCLA Library Special Collections
Sarah Bixby Smith correspondence
1871-1935
UCLA Library Special Collections
Bixby Smith, Sarah
LSC.0223
1.0 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Sarah Hathaway Bixby Smith (1871-1935) was a writer and activist. Her works include: A Little Girl of Old California (ca.1920), My Sage-brush Garden (1924), Adobe Days (1925), Pasear; a second book of California verse (1926), Wind Upon my Face (1930), Milestones in Los Angeles: being a brief narrative of Los Angeles through five decades (ca. 1933) and The Bending Tree (1933). She was significantly involved in women's groups such as the Friday Morning Club and the American Association of University Women. The collection consists primarily of correspondence and also includes announcements, invitations, photographs, and family keepsakes.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Smith Family.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303823606533
Biography
Sarah Hathaway Bixby Smith was born to Lewellyn Bixby and Mary Hathaway Bixby in August 1871, in San Justo Ranch near San Juan Bautista, California. She graduated with a bachelor's degree from Wellesley College in 1894 and was an advocate for women's independence and higher education. She was married twice, first to Arthur Maxson Smith in 1896, and then in 1916 to Paul Jordan Smith, whom she later divorced. From both marriages combined she had five children: Maxson, Bradford, Rodger, Janet, and Lewellyn. Her works include: A Little Girl of Old California (ca.1920), My Sage-brush Garden (1924), Adobe Days (1925), Pasear; a second book of California verse (1926), Wind Upon my Face (1930), Milestones in Los Angeles: being a brief narrative of Los Angeles through five decades (ca. 1933) and The Bending Tree (1933). She was the vice president of the America Association of University Women, as well as the president of the Friday Morning Club. She was also a trustee of Scripps College and a member of the Claremont School Board. In the early 1930s she was a delegate to the Pacific Relations Conference in Shanghai. She died in 1935 at the age of 64. At the time of her death she was in the process of writing another book on the history of southern California.
Scope and Content
Collection consists primarily of correspondence in the form of letters, telegrams, and postcards related to writer Sarah Bixby Smith and her family. The collection also includes announcements, invitations, photographs, and family keepsakes.
Related Material
Smith, Sarah Bixby. A little girl of old California. Los Angeles, 1920.
Smith, Sarah Bixby. Milestones in Los Angeles: being a brief narrative of Los Angeles through five decades. 1933.
Smith, Sarah Bixby. Poems selected for Americanization classes. Los Angeles: Los Angeles City School, 1929.
Correspondence.; Women authors, American -- Archives.; Bixby Smith, Sarah, 1871-1935--Correspondence.
- Correspondence between Lewellyn Bixby and Mary Hathaway, 1871-1878. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Majority of correspondence is between Lewellyn and Mary Bixby. There are a couple of letters from Lewellyn and Mary to other friends and family.
- Correspondence from Lewellyn Bixby to Sarah Bixby Smith, 1876-1894. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence from Sarah Bixby Smith to Lewellyn Bixby, 1880-1892. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes receipts from boarding school, report cards and general correspondence between Sarah and her father Lewellyn.
- Correspondence from Sarah Bixby Smith to Lewellyn Bixby, 1893. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  General correspondence between Sarah and her father Lewellyn.
- Lewellyn Bixby's Estate, 1897-1925. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Contains legal documents concerning Sarah's father's estate.
- Correspondence from friends and family concerning the death of Sarah's mother and father, 1882-1896. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence from Martha Hathaway to Sarah Bixby Smith, 1882-1928. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  This folder includes two letters from Martha Hathaway to Sarah's first husband Arthur Smith.
- Correspondence from Sarah Bixby Smith to Martha Hathaway, 1923-1924. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Majority of correspondence is from Sarah to her aunt Martha, when she was visiting London.
- Correspondence from Maxson, Bradford, and Lewellyn to their Mother Sarah Bixby Smith, 1905-1935. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes a letter written from Maxson to his sister Janet.
- Correspondence from family to Lewellyn, Bradford, Roger and Maxson Smith, 1902-1912. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Majority of letters are from Arthur Maxson Smith Sr. to his sons Lewellyn, Bradford, Roger, and Maxson.
- Invitations and Announcements, 1896-1935. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Mostly consists of the wedding announcements of Sarah's children, plus her own to Paul Smith.
- Correspondence from family/friends to Sarah Bixby Smith, 1881-1894. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically.
- Correspondence from family/friends to Sarah Bixby Smith, 1900-1924. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Correspondence from family/friends to Sarah Bixby Smith, 1925-1935. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence from Paul Smith to Sarah Bixby Smith, ca. 1934. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Adobe Days Finances, 1932. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Two reports outlining the number of books published and sold per month during 1932.
- Press Clippings, ca. 1930-1935. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Press relating to the American Association of University Women, Sarah's published poetry, and her death.
- Photographs and keepsakes, undated. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Photographs of Sarah, her first husband Arthur, and their children; also a family tree of Sarah's paternal relatives, the Bixbys.
- Autograph Book, undated. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  An autograph book signed by Sarah's family and friends.